Guide to the Joseph W. Greene Research Notes circa 1926–1939 MS 3122
New-York Historical Society
Joseph W. Greene research notes
circa 1926–1939
New-York Historical Society
Greene, Joseph Warren, 1875-1939.
MS 3122
8 Linear feet (in 8 record cartons)
Research notes on historical topics—transportation by stage, steam, and rail; inns, streets, and land grants—pertaining to New York and New England, assembled by Joseph Warren Greene Jr. (1875–1939), who contributed at least two articles to The New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin in the 1920s.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession information is lacking for this collection, which probably came to the New-York Historical Society sometime after Joseph W. Greene's death on June 13, 1939.
Arrangement
The collection is not processed. It consists almost entirely of handwritten notes in folders, or notes that are gathered in softcover report binders, and, occasionally, in loose bundles. Before being rehoused in archival record cartons, the collection was stored in twelve deteriorating boxes in no apparent order, with related materials scattered throughout multiple boxes. That remains the case, but this finding aid lists the folder/binder titles alphabetically (with some grouped geographically), in an attempt to reunite Greene's full research on specific topics. Additions and clarifications by the archivist appear in [square brackets].
Biographical note
Joseph Warren Greene Jr. (1875–1939), a Brooklyn-born lawyer admitted to the bar in 1902, retired from practice in 1919, and from the 1920s until his death pursued research on historical topics pertaining to New York City and State, New Jersey (his adopted home), and New England. Greene, who was a member of the New Jersey Society of Colonial Wars and the New Jersey Historical Society, contributed to the latter's Proceedings, and published at least two articles in the New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin in 1926 and 1927.
Related Materials
The New Jersey Historical Society holds a similar collection of Greene's research notes, though focused on New Jersey topics and localities, under its Manuscript Group 750: jerseyhistory.org/manuscript-group-750-joseph-warren-greene-jr-1875-1939-historianresearch-notes-ca-1930-1939/.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Joseph W. Greene's copious manuscript notes—a handful are typed—pertaining to the topics of transportation by stage, steam, and rail in 18th- and 19th-century New York City and the surrounding region, as well as his researches into the streets, inns, taverns, and land grants of the day. Some of this material clearly went into Greene's published work, most notably the two articles he contributed to the New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin: "New York City's First Railroad, The New York and Harlem, 1832 to 1867," vol. 9, no. 4 (January 1926), and "Mount Vernon on the East River and Colonel William Stephens Smith," vol. 10, no. 4 (January 1927).
Research notes.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Steam-navigation.; Long Island (N.Y.); Long Island Sound (N.Y. and Conn.); New England.; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Rhode Island.; Railroads -- New York (State) -- New York.; Real property -- New York (State) -- New York.; Stagecoaches.; Steamboats -- New York (State); Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; Taverns (Inns); Transportation -- New York (State) -- New York.
- "1826–1827" [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- "1831–1832" [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- "1833–1835" [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- "1839–1843" [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- "1844–1846" [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- Boston and New York Stage Coaches Pease and Sykes [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- Boston and New York Stages, 1783–1790 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Boston and New York Stages, 1791–1824 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Boston and New York Stages, 1825–184- [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Boston and Providence R.R., 1833–date [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Casey Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Connecticut] Connecticut Hotels. New Haven Hotels. [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Connecticut] Stonington R.R. I [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Connecticut] Stonington, Conn. II [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Edward Hutchinson; South Cole Farm; Rome Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Fall River Line [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- George and John Remsen [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Harlem Road IA [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Harlem Road IB [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Harlem R.R. [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Hellgate East River Misc. [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- Hudson River [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- Hudson River Inns. East Side [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- Hudson River Inns. West Side [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- Hudson River. Steam Boats I, 1800–1814 [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- Hudson River. Transportation. Stages. East Side, 1730–1786 [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- Hudson River. Transportation. Stages. East Side, 1787–1813 [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- Hudson River. Transportation. Stages. East Side. III. 1814–1836 [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- Hudson River. Transportation. Stages. East Side. IV. 1837 onward [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- Hudson River. Transportation. Stages. West Side [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- Italy [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- Long Island to Boston [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- Mandeville Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Mandeville Orchard [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Martha's Vineyard—Eliz. Isles [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- Misc. [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- Misc. [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Misc. Transportation [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- Myers Farm Lots #6 to #8 [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Myers Farm?] North ½ of lot 9; lot 10 [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New England] N.E. Steam Boats, 1867 to date [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New England] New England Stages [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New England] New England Stages [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- New Haven Road I [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- New Haven Road; Harlem Road; II; 1844 & 1848 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- New Haven Rail Road; Harlem Rail Road; 1849 [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- New Haven Road; Harlem Road; III [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- New Haven Road; Harlem Road; IV [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- New Haven Rail Road V; Harlem Rail Road; 1859–1869 [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- New Haven Rail Road VI; Harlem Rail Road; 1869 to Date [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- New Jersey Central Rail Road, 1836–1864 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- New Jersey Central RR [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn and Jamaica Road—Fulton Street [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn Heights Dutch Patents [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn Heights Jackson Farm Clark Street to Love Lane [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn Heights Pierrepont Estate [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn Heights S of Joralemon St [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn Life, vol. 53, no. 1360 (March 25, 1916) [loose issue] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Brooklyn Streets [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Coney Island to 1869 [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Coney Island, 1870–1878 [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Coney Island, 1879– [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Coney Island, 1880–1881 [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Coney Island, 1882– [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Ferry to Clark St. [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Flatbush [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Hendrick Remsen Farm, 1768–1835 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Joralemon Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Middagh Farm / Hicks Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] New Utrecht and Bath [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Pierrepont Estate [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] South of Brooklyn Heights [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] Williamsburg [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] I. Pierrepont Estate North of Pierrepont St.; I. Debevoise Tract [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Brooklyn] II. South of Pierrepont Street [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] 1. Shoemaker's Pasture; 2. Vandercliff's Estate; The Plantation of Cornelius Van Tienhoven Maiden Lane to Ann St. [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] 42nd Street [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Above Canal Street [envelope] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Above Manhattanville [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Apthorp's Northern Demesne [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Apthorp's Southern Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Archibald Gracie [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan?] Bank Coffee House [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Beekman Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Beyond the Freshwater West Side Park Row [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Bloomingdale [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Bloomingdale Estate of John M'Vickar. Hudson River Shore between 84th and 89th Streets (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Broadway East Side Bowling Green to Wall Street [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Broadway East Side Pine to Cedar Street [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Broadway north of City Hall Park; Negroe's [sic] Burial Gd [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Carmansville [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] City Stages—East Side [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Manhattan] City Stages—West Side [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Common Lands to 88th Street (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Crystal Palace, Reservoir Square I [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Crystal Palace, Reservoir Square II, 1857–1881 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Delancey's Ground [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Delancey's Land [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Dey Street [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Dove Tavern [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Early Days of the Bank of New York (n.d.) [pamphlet] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] East Bayard Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] East River, 49th to 56th Street [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] East Side Broadway Bowling Greene to Wall Street [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] East Side Misc. [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] East Side S of Wall St. [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] From 42nd Street to Turtle Bay [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Greenwich Village [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Harlem [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Hendrick Brevoort Farm Lands [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Herring Farm I [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Herring Farm II [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Interior New York [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Jacob Harsen Farm, Bloomingdale [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Jones' Wood [bound; December 1933] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] King's Color-Graphs of New York City (1910) [pamphlet] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Kips Bay & Beyond [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Kips Bay—Bellevue [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Kip's Bay—Bellevue [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Manhattanville [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Mount Vernon [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Murray Hill [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] N.Y. Misc. [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Manhattan] N.Y. Streets [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] N.Y.C. Transportation Elevated Roads [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan?] Elevated Roads, Etc. [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] No. 1 Broadway [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] North of Manhattanville [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Oliver DeLancey's Plantation [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] One of the oldest buildings on Manhattan Island... [loose typescript] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Other Side Fulton St. [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Richmond Hill [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Roger Morris or Jumel House [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Rose Hill Farm II, 1823–date [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Sir Peter Warren [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Sir Peter Warren... [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Story of 42nd Street [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Stuyvesant's Pear Tree [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Teunis Somerendyke I (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Teunis Somerendyke II; Oakley's Bloomingdale [Houses? Leases?] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Third Avenue at Rose Hill [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] To the Freshwater [envelope] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Town of Harlem. Patent of Abraham Shotwell [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] [Trinity Church farm?] [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Vauxhall Farm [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Vineyard. Park Row to [Bar?] [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Wall Street N/S [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Wall Street N/Side [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Washington Heights [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Washington's Rock [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York City—Manhattan] West side Broadway north of Chambers Street [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Manhattan] Yorkville [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York City—Queens] Long Island—Astoria & Hell Gate [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Queens] Flushing and Long Island Misc. [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York City—Queens] Rockaway, L.I., 1759–1836 [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Queens] Rockaway, L.I., 1838 to date [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [New York City—Staten Island] Staten Island [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York City—Staten Island or Manhattan?] Sailor's Snug Harbor [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin Index, Vol. X, April, 1926–January 1927 [loose leaflet] (Offsite-box 7)
- New York Misc. [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- New York Schools, 1825 on [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- New York Schools to 1830 [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York State] Battle of Plattsburgh: What Historians Say About It (1914) [pamphlet] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York State] Misc. N.Y. State [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York State] Mohawk & Hudson RR [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York State] Mohawk & Hudson II [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York State] Mohawk & Hudson RR [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York State] New York State RR [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [New York State] New York State Stages Canals Boats [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York State—Long Island] Long Island [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York State—Long Island] Long Island [bound; Done May 1937] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York State—Long Island] East End of L.I. Shelter Island Gardiners Is. [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- [New York State—Long Island] Fisher's Island [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- [New York State—Long Island] Long Island Railroad 100th Anniversary (1934) [pamphlet] (Offsite-box 1)
- [New York State—Long Island] Long Island Sea Rack and Sea Wreck [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [New York State—Long Island] Long Island Sound 1835 to 1838 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York State—Long Island] Sound—Sound Steam Boats [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York State—Long Island] Sound Steamboats, 1762–1811 [bound] (Offsite-box 2)
- [New York State—Long Island] Sound Steam Boats, 1850–1867 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- New York Women Smoking, etc. [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- New York & Boston Steamboats & Stages, 1822–1823 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- New York & New Haven I / II [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- New York & New Haven Rail Road II, 1845–1848 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- New York & Phila. [folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- New York-Philadelphia, 1675–1783 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [New York-Philadelphia?], 1784–1800 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Patent of Joseph Young. Patent of John Banyar[?] [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Pennsylvania] Pennsylvania [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- [Pennsylvania] Philadelphia & South II from 1700 [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- Philip Livingston's Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- Post Riders [folder] (Offsite-box 2)
- President Lincoln [loose notes] (Offsite-box 1)
- Racing, etc. [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- Railroads [loose notes] (Offsite-box 1)
- Rapid Transit [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Red House [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [Rhode Island] John Gardiner's Westquage [Wesquage] Beach. The Bonnet [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Rhode Island] John Watkins Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- [Rhode Island] Newport I—To 1848 [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Rhode Island] Newport 1874 to Date [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Rhode Island] Pettaquamscutt Purchase, Gilbert Stewart's Snuff Mill [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Rhode Island] Pettaquamscutt Purchase, West side Narrow River [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Rhode Island] Providence I [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Rhode Island] Providence II [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Rhode Island] Providence III [bound] (Offsite-box 8)
- [Rhode Island] Wickford and Newport Railroad Steamboat Company, 1864–1871 [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Rhode Island] Wickford and Newport Railroad & Steamboat Company II, June 5, 1871 to date [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- [Rhode Island] Wickford Village, West Main Street, South Side [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Saybrook to South Ferry to Providence [bound] (Offsite-box 1)
- South & West Travel [bound] (Offsite-box 6)
- Stage Coach Upsets [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Stage Coaches, 1800–1809 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Stage Coaches, 1822–1826 [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Stages Suburban [folder] (Offsite-box 1)
- Steamboats / Stages South & West [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Steamboats 1785–1807 [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Summer Resorts [folder] (Offsite-box 6)
- Thomas B. Bridgen [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- Transportation New York to Boston via L. I., 1844–1847 [bound] (Offsite-box 1)
- W. H. Vail, DIV-A-LET. Division by Letters. A Pastime or Mental Diversion, Mostly Intended for Those Who are Fond of Such Things (1909) [booklet] (Offsite-box 7)
- Weather, etc. [bound] (Offsite-box 7)
- Westchester & etc. [bound] (Offsite-box 4)
- Western Rail Road [bound] (Offsite-box 5)
- William Ogden's Ogden Place Farm [bound] (Offsite-box 3)
- Unidentified notes [1 bundle] (Offsite-box 1)
- Unidentified notes [3 bundles] (Offsite-box 4)
- Unidentified notes [1 folder] (Offsite-box 4)
- Unidentified notes [in small notebooks & loose] (Offsite-box 4)
- Unidentified notes [2 binders] (Offsite-box 5)
- Unidentified notes [2 bundles] (Offsite-box 5)
- Unidentified notes [3 binders] (Offsite-box 6)
- Unidentified notes [2 bundles] (Offsite-box 6)
- Unidentified notes [2 folders] (Offsite-box 6)
- Unidentified notes [4 binders] (Offsite-box 7)
- Unidentified notes [1 bundle] (Offsite-box 7)
- Unidentified notes [1 binder] (Offsite-box 8)
- Unidentified notes [1 bundle] (Offsite-box 8)